Guide to the Kathy Acker Papers, 1972-1997 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Kathy Acker papers 1972-1997 and undated
Acker, Kathy, 1948-
20.7 linear feet Extent: 3860 Items
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
RL.00011
Language: English.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
Also, some of the materials in this collection are not immediately accessible, because they require further processing before use.
Furthermore, all or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. There may be a 48-hour delay in obtaining these materials.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Kathy Acker Papers was received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a purchase in 1999-2002, 2012, 2014.
Biographical Note
1948 Born.
1963-65 Studied Classics at Brandeis University.
1967 Received BA from University of California at San Diego (UCSD).
1968-1970 Studied at UCSD Department of Literature.
1971 Studied at New York University Classics Department.
1975 Published The Childlike Life of the Black Tarantula.
1975-1976 Creative Artists' Public Services Program New York State Grant For Fiction.
1978 Published Kathy Goes to Haiti.
1980 Published I Dreamt I Became A Nymphomaniac: Imagining.
1980 Published The Adult Life of Toulouse-Lautrec.
1980-1981 Instructor, The San Francisco Art Institute, Video and Performance Department.
1981 Pushcart Prize.
1982 Published Hello, I'm Erica Jong.
1983 Published Great Expectations.
1984 Published Algeria: A Series of Invocations Because Nothing Else Works.
1984 Published Blood and Guts in High School.
1986 Published Don Quixote.
1988 Published Empire of the Senseless.
1988 My Death, My Life, By Pier Paolo Pasolini published in Literal Madness.
1989 Published Young Lust; Kathy Goes to Haiti; The Adult Life of Toulouse Lautrec; Florida.
1990 Published The Seven Cardinal Virtues.
1990 Published In Memoriam to Identity.
1991 Published Hannibal Lecteur, My Father.
1991-1995 Adjunct Professor, San Francisco Art Institute.
1992 Published Portrait of an Eye: Three Novels.
1993 Published My Mother Demonology.
1994 Visiting Professor, UCSD.
1994 Visiting Professor, University of California at Santa Barbara.
1994 Visiting Professor, University of Idaho.
1996 Published Pussy, King of the Pirates.
1997 Died.
Collection Overview
The papers of Kathy Acker, 1975-1996 and undated, are comprised, for the most part, of manuscript drafts of her novels, short stories, and other miscellaneous writings ranging from early works such as The Childlike Life of the Black Tarantula (1975) to her last novel Pussy, King of the Pirates (1996). Described as a cyberpunk author and performance artist, Acker's novels question the strictures of female sexuality and the power of language.
The collection is divided into the Writing Series (with subseries of Manuscript Drafts and Miscellaneous Drafts), Audio Cassettes Series, Correspondence Series, and Artwork Series. The Writing Series contains corrected typescripts, photocopies or original holograph manuscripts of Blood and Guts in High School, Don Quixote, Empire of the Senseless, Great Expectations, In Memoriam to Identity, Kathy Goes to Haiti, My Death, My Life by Pier Paolo Pasolini, My Mother Demonology, Tarantula Nympho-Lautrec Trilogy, The Childlike Life of the Black Tarantula, I Dreamt I Became a Nymphomaniac!: Imagining, The Adult Life of Toulouse Lautrec, Ripoff Red: Girl Detective and Pussy, King of the Pirates. There are also drafts of the play The Birth of the Poet, the filmscript Variety, and short stories such as The Language of the Body, Jean Duval, and Girl Gangs Take Over the World.
The Audio Cassette Series primarily consists of cassette recordings of interviews with Acker or lectures given by Acker.
The Correspondence Series contains letters from people offering suggestions on Acker's works or from others asking for or thanking Acker for her suggestions regarding their works. Also included are essays and poetry sent to Acker as well as other letters from friends and colleagues. (Includes correspondence from accession #1999-0207.)
The Artwork Series contains original artwork for Empire of the Senseless, In Memoriam to Identity, Blood and Guts in High School, I Dreamt I Became a Nymphomaniac, and Pussy, King of the Pirates. In addition, there are numerous black and white photographs of Acker by Robert Mapplethorpe and Marcus Leatherdale.
The addition (99-207) (75 items, .1 linear ft.; dated 1973-1978) contains two lengthy sections from Acker's spiralbound notebook, one recording dreams, fantasies and events in her typical stream of consciousness manner, the second containing reflections on various topics and thinkers, including de Sade. There is an original typescript of an introduction for her book, The Thesmophoriazisae; an early version of The Childlike Life of the Black Tarantula #6; The Story of My Life, a home-made production in the original format Acker used to distribute her work; twenty-five letters from other poets and writers, including Andrei Codrescu, Kenneth Rexroth, Jack Hirschman, Fielding Dawson, Ed Dron, Ed Sanders, Laura Chester, Peter Gordon, Rex Pickett, Opal Nations, and Barbara Baracks (interfiled in the Correspondence Series); and an original color broadside announcing a reading by Acker. All materials from accession #1999-0207, except correspondence, are interfiled with accession #2002-0081.
The addition (2002-0081) (3552 items, 6.5 linear feet; dated [ca. 1979]-1997 and undated) includes correspondence, drafts, and notebooks of works by Acker, writings about Acker, photographs, and audio recordings. The drafts and notebooks include numerous edited and unedited typescripts of Acker's books Pussy, King of the Pirates; Eurydice in the Underworld; and Requiem. There are also drafts and research material for the articles Sugar and Spice, based on an interview with the Spice Girls, and The Gift of Disease, dealing with her battle with cancer. Also includes 927 electronic documents on 2 zip disks and 3, 3.5" floppies; 3 audiocassettes; 3 CDs; 1 LP; 7 black-and-white and 6 color photographs; 5 color negatives; and two color slides.
The addition (2002-0164) (2 items, .1 linear feet; dated ca. 1972) is a photocopy of Acker's 59-page typescript, "The Destruction of the U.S./The Burning Bombing of America." Includes a 3-page document by Susan Orlofsky describing the typescript's provenance and outlining its contents. (This accession has been interfiled with Acc. 2002-0081.)
Subject Headings
Acker, Kathy, 1948-; My mother demonology.; In memoriam to identity.; Don Quixote.; Great expectations.; Girl gangs take over the world.; Childlike life of the black tarantula.; I dreamt I became a nymphomaniac!: imagining.; Adult life of Toulouse-Lautrec.; Variety.; Ripoff Red: Girl detective.; Empire of the senseless.; Blood and guts in high school.; Pussy, King of the Pirates.; Thesmophoriazusae.; Story of My Life.; American fiction -- Women authors; American fiction -- 20th century; Punk culture -- United States -- Fiction; Experimental fiction -- Women authors; Authors, American -- 20th century -- Correspondence; Machine-readable records; Audiocassettes; Color slides; Color photographs; Color negatives; Black-and-white negatives; CD-ROMs; Phonograph record
Contents of Collection
- Writings Series
  - Manuscript Drafts
    - Novels
      - Blood and Guts in High School, (2 folders) (Box 1)
        - Blood and Guts in High School (Box 1)
          Proofs
        - Blood and Guts in High School (Box 1)
      - Don Quixote, (2 volumes) (Box 1)
        - Volume I (Box 1)
          Approximately 189 pages of original typescript, computer printout and photocopied typescript, with some original corrections. Enclosed in black binding.
        - Volume III (Box 1)
          Approximately 80 pages of original typescript and photocopies, moderately corrected by Acker with additions and deletions. Enclosed in black binding.
      - Empire of the Senseless (Box 1)
      - Great Expectations, (2 folders) (Box 1)
        - Folder 1 (Box 1)
          Approximately 300-page original typescript and photocopies, moderately corrected by Acker.
        - Folder 2 (Box 1)
          Blues
      - In Memoriam to Identity, (1 folder) (Box 1)
      - In Memoriam to Identity. 1988-1989., (2 volumes) (Box 2)
        - Volume I (Box 2)
          112-page photocopied typescript with some original corrections and some corrections in the photocopy. Enclosed in red binding.
        - Volume II (Box 2)
          188-page photocopied typescript with some original corrections. Enclosed in black binding.
      - Kathy Goes to Haiti (Box 2)
      - Kathy Goes to Haiti (Box 2)
      - My Death, My Life by Pier Paolo Pasolini (Box 2)
      - My Mother Demonology, (4 volumes) (Box 2)
        - My Mother Demonology (Box 2)
        - My Mother Demonology--"My Mother" (Chapters I and II), (2 volumes) (Box 3)
          - Spiral notebook, 7 x 8.25 inches. (Box 3)
            57-page original holograph manuscript of part one, with many additions and deletions.
          - Spiral notebook, 6 x 9.5 inches. (Box 3)
            123-page original holograph manuscript of parts one and two, with corrections.
        - My Mother Demonology--"Clit City" (Chapter III), (5 volumes) (Box 3)
          - Spiral notebook, 5.75 x 8.25 inches. (Box 3)
            62-page original holograph manuscript, with a few corrections.
          - Spiral notebook, 6 x 9.5 inches. (Box 3)
            51-page original holograph, with a few corrections.
          - Spiral notebook, 6 x 9.5 inches. (Box 3)
            73-page original holograph manuscript, heavily corrected with many additions and deletions.
          - Spiral notebook, 5.75 x 8.25 inches. (Box 3)
            80-page original holograph manuscript, with some corrections.
          - Spiral notebook, 6.75 x 8.25 inches. (Box 3)
            85-page original holograph manuscript, with deletions and additions.
        - My Mother Demonology--"Obsession" (Chapter IV), (3 volumes) (Box 3)
          - Spiral notebook, 6 x 9.5 inches. (Box 3)
            42-page original holograph manuscript first draft, with many corrections.
          - Spiral notebook, 7 x 8.25 inches. (Box 3)
            50-page original holograph manuscript second draft, with some additions and deletions.
          - Spiral notebook, 7 x 8.25 inches. (Box 3)
            60-page original holograph manuscript second draft, with many additions and deletions.
        - My Mother Demonology--"Dreaming Politics" (Chapter V), (5 volumes) (Box 3)
          - Spiral notebook, 6 x 9.5 inches, entitled, "First draft of certain sections." (Box 3)
            66-page original holograph manuscript with a few additions and deletions.
          - Spiral notebook, 7 x 8.25 inches, entitled, "First, second drafts mainly second draft of dream sections." (Box 3)
            58-page original holograph manuscript, with some additions and deletions.
          - Spiral notebook, 7 x 8.25 inches, entitled, "Beginning of Book." (Box 3)
          - Spiral notebook, 7 x 8.25 inches, entitled, "3rd draft, indications of uses of second draft..." (Box 3)
            51-page original holograph manuscript, heavily corrected with additions and deletions.
          - Spiral notebook, 7 x 8.25 inches, entitled, "Last handwritten draft--changed according to oral reading." (Box 3)
            34-page original holograph manuscript, heavily corrected with additions and deletions.
        - My Mother Demonology--"Redoing Childhood" (Chapter VI), (3 volumes) (Box 3)
          - Spiral notebook, 7 x 8.25 inches. (Box 3)
            73-page original holograph manuscript first draft, with some additions and deletions.
          - Spiral notebook, 7 x 8.25 inches. (Box 3)
            48-page original holograph manuscript first draft, with some additions and deletions.
          - Spiral notebook, 7 x 8.25 inches. (Box 3)
            65-page original holograph manuscript final draft, heavily corrected with many additions and deletions.
        - My Mother Demonology--""The Dead Man" (Chapter VII), (4 volumes) (Box 3)
          - Spiral notebook, 7 x 8.25 inches. (Box 3)
            84-page original holograph manuscript, with many corrections, additions and deletions.
          - Spiral notebook, 7 x 8.25 inches. (Box 3)
            54-page original holograph manuscript, corrected, with some additions and deletions.
          - Spiral notebook, 7 x 8.25 inches. (Box 3)
            Insert entitled, "Dreams for book and end of 'The Dead Man.'" 45-page original holograph manuscript, with a few corrections.
          - Spiral notebook, 7 x 8.25 inches. (Box 3)
            Insert entitled, "'The Dead Man'--End Final draft." 14-page original holograph manuscript, heavily corrected with additions and deletions.
      - Original of Tarantula Nympho-Lautrec Trilogy (Box 3)
        Now collected as Portrait of an Eye: Three Novels, Pantheon.
        - The Childlike Life of the Black Tarantula. By The Black Tarantula. (Box 3)
          Small 8vo. Original pictorial wrappers (New York: Tvrt Press, 1978). First Edition. Limited. With some ink corrections to the text by Acker.
          Copy "July '73 #3," original trial paste-up copy.
        - I Dreamt I Became a Nymphomaniac!: Imagining. (Box 3)
          8 vo. Original printed beige wrappers (San Francisco 1974). Inscribed on the cover, "for PP & CP from his dearly beloved--TBT."
          8 vo. Original printed beige wrappers (San Francisco 1974). With marks on cover: "'Carworth' Rat + mouse breeders in High Falls --ask for slightly used-- 26 Nov 74." On back cover: "Bargyla Alyabgy Babylrgy"
        - I Dreamt I Became a Nymphomaniac!: Imagining. Part 2. (Box 3)
          Original plain white wrappers. Inscribed on the cover, "This is for CP & PP who has to be around 1 day a week. This will make him be around--TBT." With some corrections and underlining in the text by Acker.
        - I Dreamt I Became a Nymphomaniac!: Imagining. Part 3. (Box 3)
          Original printed white wrappers (printed "Peter Gordon 1974") and inscribed by Acker, "(Note: Fred: Not by Peter, but I said by him as a present to him. I was always changing my name in those days.)"
        - I Dreamt I Became a Nymphomaniac!: Imagining. Part 4. (Box 3)
          Original printed white wrappers. Inscribed by Acker on the cover, "for the person who helped me do this. The Black Tarantula," with a drawing of three hearts.
        - I Dreamt I Became a Nymphomaniac!: Imagining. Part 5. (Box 3)
          Original printed white wrappers.
        - I Dreamt I Became a Nymphomaniac!: Imagining. Part 6. (Box 3)
        - Another complete, clean copy of Nymphomaniac (missing Part 6). (Box 3)
        - The Adult Life of Toulouse Lautrec. (Box 3)
          Illustrated. Small 8vo. Original pictorial wrappers (New York: Tvrt Press, 1978). First Edition. Limited.
      - Ripoff Red: Girl Detective (Box 3)
        Early unpublished novel, 1973. Original 154-page typescript with some typed corrections. Enclosed in black binding with hand-lettered label. With original holograph title page and drawing by Acker.
    - Plays and Film Scripts (Box 3)
      - The Birth of the Poet (Box 3)
      - The Birth of the Poet [in So & So, 2:1] (Box 3)
      - Variety (Box 3)
        A film written for director Bette Gordon. 46-page typescript, with notations and corrections by Acker.
    - Shorter Works (Box 3)
      - The Language of the Body [short story] (Box 4)
        - Spiral notebook, 7 x 8.25". (Box 4)
          31-page original holograph manuscript first draft, with additions and deletions.
        - Spiral notebook, 7 x 8.25". (Box 4)
          20-page original holograph manuscript second draft, with many additions and deletions.
      - Jeane Duval [short story] (Box 4)
        - Spiral notebook, 6.5 x 9.5". (Box 4)
          21-page original holograph manuscript, with some deletions.
        - Spiral notebook, 6.5 x 9.5". (Box 4)
          45-page original holograph manuscript, with a few corrections.
      - Girl Gangs Take Over the World (1979) (Box 4)
        An early version of Algeria, which appears in Hannibal Lecteur, My Father. Approximately 100-page original typescript, with some corrections by Acker. Enclosed in blue folder. Farsi Text originals
      - Lust/A Sailor's Slight Identity (Box 4)
      - Loss/The Memory of Orpheus (Box 4)
      - Florida and Cesar Vallejo Poems (Box 4)
      - New York City in 1979: To Jeanne's Insulted Beauty (Box 4)
        60-page photocopied typescript, corrected in the photocopy, with original note on the title page, My Copy, by Acker.
      - Journal Black Cats Black Jewels, (Summer 1972) (Box 4)
        Original 9-page typescript with a few typed corrections; stapled into gray wrappers.
      - Entrance Into Dwelling in Paradise, (Fall 1972) (Box 4)
        Original 7-page typescript with a few typed corrections; laid into orange wrappers.
      - Exercise #3: Writing Asystematically. Murderers-Criminals Join Sunlight. (Box 4)
        Original 8-page typescript, with a few holograph corrections; laid into blue wrappers
      - Homage to Leroi Jones, (Fall 1972) (Box 4)
        12-page photocopied typescript
      - Peter Gordon: Ambiguity., 1981 (Box 4)
        Original 22-page typescript with typed corrections
      - Nightmare City. (Box 4)
        19-page photocopied typescript with a few holograph corrections by Acker in the photocopy.
      - The Seattle Book: For Randy and Heather., 1980. (Box 4)
        14-page photocopied typescript with original typed title page.
      - Conversations., 1974. (Box 4)
        Original 9-page typescript, with typed corrections.
      - Small Texts. (Box 4)
        Approximately 70 pages of typescript and photocopy, with a few typed and holograph corrections. Enclosed in yellow folder with hand-lettered label. Text includes the short stories: Christ Comes to New York City, Notes on Writing from The Life of Baudelaire, The Rebel, The Bum, Voodoo, Blood and Guts in High School, For the Ladies Who Sing: Three Stories, 1977, The Scorpions, Lady Be Bad.
      - Various Small Texts with corrections. (Box 4)
        46 pages of typescript, lightly corrected, including: Two Girls, The Underside of Dream, Spring Touring, In the Days Before Dreaming... faxed to John Zorn, The Travels of the Pirates: These Beginnings..., J, piece beginning When the divine Marquis, as some have named him, in his Philosophy in the Bedroom..., which includes Theoretical Language in a Patriarchal Society, The Language of the Body, and Non-Patriarchal Language: The Body.
    - Magazine Articles (Box 4)
      - Miscellaneous. (Box 4)
        7-page typescript and photocopy of works in progress, with some corrections; plus L=A=N=G=U=A=G=E. Number 9/10. October 1979. Containing Notes on Writing--from The Life of Baudelaire by Acker. Original self cover; plus Fete by Acker (1980). Folded photocopied typescript, 1 page (14 copies); plus Looking for Madonna, (for Saturday Review), 3-page photocopy with 2 holograph corrections by Acker.
      - Small Pieces. (Box 4)
        Approximately 65 pages of photocopied typescript, with typed and holograph corrections.
      - Miscellaneous Articles. (Box 4)
        Approximately 30 pages of photocopied typescript with some original holograph corrections. Articles for The Village Voice and The New Statesman.
      - Reading the Lack of the Body: The Writing of the Marquis de Sade., 1992. (Box 4)
        Approximately 30-page typescript.
      - My Mother., 1990-1. (Box 4)
        Original 16-page typescript with many holograph corrections; plus 13-paged "reading version," corrected in the photocopy, with a few original holograph corrections; plus 19-page proofs, corrected by Acker with many additions and deletions, with a note from Brad Morrow, editor of Conjunctions magazine.
      - Rejects from Don Quixote and The Love Sonnets of a Hoodlum by Wallace Irwin. With an introduction by Gelett Burgess. New York, 1901 (Box 4)
        Original printed wrappers.
      - New York City: 1983 ["For Marcus Leatherdale Catalogue"]. (Box 4)
        8-page photocopied typescript
      - Japan, 1983 (Box 4)
        10-page photocopied typescript, corrected in the photocopy
      - Photocopy of a 2-page TLS from William Burroughs to Miles, with 10-page photocopied typescript of The Reactive Mind. (Box 4)
      - Time 1981 (Box 4)
        Translations of the Diaries of Laure. Original 18-page typescript, signed, with some corrections by Acker; plus 2-page proof, with 3 corrections by Acker.
      - For Ariane. 1990-1. Writings. (Box 4)
        Approximately 50 pages of typescripts, with some corrections by Acker.
      - Me Talking About Me. Magazine Articles. (Box 4)
      - Red Wings: Concerning Richard Prince's Spiritual America. (Box 4)
        Original 10-page typescript, with signed fax from Acker; plus approximately 50 pages of miscellaneous photocopied typescripts, with some corrections by Acker; plus 13-page photocopied typescript interview with Acker on April 23, 1986, conducted by Dick Ellis, et al.
      - More Short Pieces, 1989 (Box 4)
        Approximately 100 pages of photocopied typescript, with some ink notations by Acker.
      - Vogue (Meare) London Times (exile) (Box 4)
        5-page typescript review of Bonfire of the Vanities, signed, for The New Statesman.
      - Freedom and Domination in the Theatre. A Working Diary. (Box 4)
        8-page photocopied typescript with some original corrections.
      - Miscellaneous Articles (Box 4)
        4-page original typescript; plus approximately 25 pages of photocopied typescript of articles and faxes, copy of poetry festival program.
        - Motorcycle insurance policy, dated 1989 (Box 4)
        - William Burroughs' Realism. (Box 4)
        - 6th Bisbee Poetry Festival program. (Box 4)
- Audio Cassettes (Box 4)
  - Kathy Acker and British astrologer discuss Acker's astrological chart (Box 4)
  - Tape from Acker's answering machine, London (Box 4)
    Side 2 is blank
  - Kathy Acker with Nox: Love, Emily [from My Death, My Life, By Pier Paolo Pasolini] (Box 4)
  - Kathy Acker and an unidentified British art critic (?) walk through an Andy Warhol exhibit, discussing Warhol and the Pop Art movement (Box 4)
  - German radio show on Acker's work (Box 4)
    In German; narration about/by Kathy mixed with complete (lengthy) rock songs--artists named on Side 2. Side 2 also contains an unrelated radio show that followed the Acker special.
  - Lecture by Acker on Wuthering Heights, Maurice Blanchot and literary tradition. (Box 4)
- Writings Series (Box 4)
  - Manuscript Drafts (Box 4)
    - Novels (Box 4)
      - Pussy, King of the Pirates (Box 5)
        - Story of O in which everyone's an animal. (Box 5)
          Original 58-page corrected holograph manuscript in spiral-bound notebook.
        - O & Ange. Beginning. (Box 5)
          Original 53-page corrected holograph manuscript in spiral-bound notebook.
        - "Second Chapter--Beginning of O & Ange." (Box 5)
          Original 26-page corrected holograph manuscript in spiral-bound notebook.
        - O & Ange. In A World Without Men. (Box 5)
          Original 49-page corrected holograph manuscript in spiral-bound notebook.
        - The World W/out Men/Thru the Cunts of Our Mothers. (Box 5)
          Original 50-page corrected holograph manuscript in black spiral-bound notebook.
        - Escape. (Box 5)
          Original 65-page corrected holograph manuscript beginning After the Death of the Whore-house--O becomes a poet, in spiral-bound notebook.